Guide to the Ari and Helene Bousbib Collection of Photographs 1879-1996 PR 384
New-York Historical Society
Ari and Helene Bousbib collection of photographs
1879-1996
New-York Historical Society
Bousbib, Ari
Bousbib, Helene
PR 384
46.6 Linear feet in 63 boxes
This collection consists of a wide variety of entertainment-themed publicity and on-set photography, portraiture, and photojournalism spanning the period from 1879-1996. Subjects depicted include Broadway theatrical productions, Hollywood film actors, artists, authors, aviators, newscasters, politicians, and other pop culture figures. Also depicted are New York sports, political activism, the 1939 World's Fair, World War II, and other events.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Scope and Contents
This collection of entertainment-themed photography and photojournalism includes publicity and on-set production coverage of films and plays; portraits of theatre performers, movie stars, athletes, politicians, and other 20th-century pop culture figures; and sports and cultural and political event photojournalism. The materials are arranged into three series.
Series I: Broadway Theatrical Photography is comprised of late 19th and 20th century publicity, production, and portrait photography. It documents the development of New York theater from 1879 through the 1980s, with images of Broadway theatrical productions, set design, and costumes. Productions ranging from comedie, revivals, operettas, melodramas, dance, musicals, revues, and Shakespearean plays are found in this series. In addition, the series contains portraits of actors from the famous to the obscure.
The work of Broadway's foremost photography agencies are represented, including Apeda Studio, Friedman-Abeles, George Maillard Kesslere, Mishkin Studio, Ben Pinchot, Sarony and Co., Martha Swope, Vandamm Studios, and White Studio.
Series II: Hollywood Studio Photography Film consists of images created by the photography units of the American film industry's major motion picture studios including Warner Bros, Universal, Paramount, RKO, Fox Corporation, and Columbia Pictures. The photos date from 1915-1990, and while most are studio portraits, there are also staged shots depicting subjects at home, with their families and friends, engaging in physical and outdoor activities, and modeling clothes.
The photographers featured in this series include, among others, John Miehle, Gene Robert Richee, Roman Freulich, Clarence Sinclair Bull, Ruth Harriet Louise, Elmer Fryer, and Robert W. Coburn.
Series III: Photojournalism and Documentary Photography contains a diverse range of work dating from 1880 to 1996. It includes the work of photojournalists Rudolph Arnold, Margaret Bourke-White, Philippe Halsman, Jill Freedman, Mary Ellen Mark, Fred McDarrah, Magnum photographers, and Ken Regan, who each documented various aspects of American life and culture in the 20th century. The work of celebrity photographers and paparazzi such as Peter Basch, Andre De Dienes, and Ron Galella is also part of this series. In addition, the series includes the work of various photography studios that specialized in subjects such as advertising and store windows (Artkraft Strauss, Worsinger) and architecture and construction (Eugene de Salignac, Wurts Bros., George P. Hall and Son). Photos from news agencies (Acme Newspictures, PM News,) and government agencies (White House Photography, WPA) are also included here.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ari and Helene Bousbib, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, and 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series. These three series are arranged according to theme:
I. Broadway Theatrical Photography
II. Hollywood Studio Photography
III. Photojournalism and Documentary Photography
Within each series, material is arranged alphabetically by creator.
Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Celebrities -- United States -- Portraits; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States -- Portraits.; Street photography -- New York (State) -- New York.; Theatrical productions -- New York (State) -- New York -- 1900-2000; World War, 1939-1945.; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111]
- Series I: Broadway Theatrical Photography, 1879-1987
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of late 19th and 20th century publicity, production, and portrait photography. It documents the development of New York theater from 1879 through the 1980s, with images of Broadway theatrical productions, set design, and costumes. Productions ranging from comedie, revivals, operettas, melodramas, dance, musicals, revues, and Shakespearean plays are found in this series. In addition, the series contains portraits of actors from the famous to the obscure.
  The work of Broadway's foremost photography agencies are represented, including Apeda Studio, Friedman-Abeles, George Maillard Kesslere, Mishkin Studio, Ben Pinchot, Sarony and Co., Martha Swope, Vandamm Studios, and White Studio.
  - Subseries: APEDA STUDIO, 1910-1934
    Biographical / Historical
    Apeda Studio was founded in 1906 by partners Alexander W. Dreyfoos (1877-1952) and Henry Obstfield. The studio was originally located at 33 West 34th Street, and Dreyfoos was the head photographer, and Obstfield managed the studio. Apeda Studios focused on sports, theater and celebrity portraiture. In addition to shooting portraits, Apeda Studios specialized in reproducing uncopyrighted images by other photographers under its own trade name. If other photographers had images that they could not reproduce and market themselves, or took a photograph that could not be copyrighted because there was no contract between photographer and sitter, Apeda would secure a print, remove whatever name or trademark appeared on the print and affixed their own Apeda signature to the copies it produced. Apeda would also buy up the entire production archive of photographers who had business difficulties or were moving to other parts of the country. During the mid-1930s Apeda shifted away from performing arts photography, turning to advertising imagery, industrial photography, and class portraiture.
    This subseries consists of Broadway theatrical publicity, production, and portrait photography produced by Apeda Studio, NY from 1910-1934. Subjects include Jimmy Durante, George Burns and Gracie Allen, Josephine McNellis, Will Mahoney, Blanche Ring, and Helen Vreeland.
    - Theatrical Portraits A-B (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Theatrical Portraits C-D (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Theatrical Portraits E-G (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Portraits H-L (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Theatrical Portraits M (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Theatrical Portraits N-Q (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Theatrical Portraits R-Z (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: FRIEDMAN-ABELES, 1955-1976
    This subseries consists of photographs and ephemera related to Broadway theatrical plays produced between 1955-1976. The photographs were taken by the Friedman-Abeles Studio between 1955 and 1976. Photographers Joseph Abeles (1908-1991) and Leo Friedman (1919-2011) began their partnership in 1954, and specialized in documenting Broadway and the theatrical world.
    Included in this subseries are stills, clippings, and playbills from many major and minor Broadway shows of the era. Among them are "Cabaret," "Camelot," "MacBeth," "A Man for All Seasons," "The Music Man," "No No Nanette," "Our Town," and "Prisoner of Second Avenue".
    - Theatrical Productions A, 1958-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Theatrical Productions B, 1958-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
    - Theatrical Productions C, 1960-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Theatrical Productions D, 1960-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Theatrical Productions E, 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Theartrical Productions F, 1961-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Theatrical Productions G-I, 1955-1975 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
    - Theatrical Productions J-L, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    - Theatrical Productions M, 1955-1975 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - Theatrical Productions N-Q, 1960-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
    - Theatrical Productions R-S, 1959-1972 (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
    - Theatrical Productions T-Z, 1958-1970 (Box 10, Folder 1-9)
    - Theatrical Portraits A-Z, 1955-1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, 1961-1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Theatrical Productions, oversize, 1939, circa 1960 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Two photos: One of Joan Collins and Warren Beatty, the other a scene from "Destry Rides Again."
  - Subseries: GEORGE MAILLARD KESSLERE, 1923-1941
    George Maillard Kesslere (1894-1979) was known for his painterly portraits of actors, celebrities, and New York society figures. He was considered one of the finest bust format photographers of the 1920s and 1930s. Kesslere opened a studio in New York City in 1921, and his work caught the attention of Broadway producer and director Earl Carroll, who installed Kesslere as his official photographer after the death of John De Mirjian in 1928. The theater programs for Carroll's "Vanities" series featured paintings and photos by Kesslere. In April 1952, Kesslere donated 6,000 photographs and 500 paintings to the Theater Collection of the New York Public Library.
    This subseries consists of theatrical portraits taken by George Maillard Kesselere between 1923-1941. Among the subjects are Mary Boland, Olga Borouska, Henry Fonda, and Rudy Vallee.
    - Theatrical Portraits A-C, 1923-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Theatrical Portraits D-Z, 1923-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries: MISHKIN STUDIO, 1913-1930
    Born in Minsk, Russia, Herman Mishkin (1871-1948) immigrated to the United States in 1885. While working as a store clerk in New York City, Mishkin began shooting cartes de visites and cabinet portraits of performers in costume in the 1890s, eventually securing a position with Oscar Hammerstein's Manhattan Opera Company as a photographer-publicist.
    In 1908, the Metropolitan Opera hired Mishkin as its official photographer, and he served as the Met's portraitist until 1932. While shooting opera stars for the Metropolitan, he maintained a portrait studio frequented by most of the significant actors and celebrities of the day.
    This subseries consists of portraits takin by Mishkin Studio between 1913-1930. Subjects include Mary Lewis, Katharine Cornell, Janet Beecher, Mario Chamlee, France Demarest, and Will Rogers.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1913-1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries: BEN PINCHOT, 1927-1945
    This series consists mainly of portraits of actors and theatrical productions taken by American photographer Ben Pinchot (1890-1986). From the 1927 through the late 1940s, Pinchot became known for his dramatic nudes, and for capturing artists and performers in their element.
    - Theatrical Portraits A-I, 1927-1945 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Theatrical Portraits J-Z, 1927-1945 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Subseries: SARONY AND CO., 1879-1917
    Napoleon Sarony (1821-1896) was the premier theatrical photographer of the 19th century. Born in Québec, Sarony moved to New York in 1836 and began his career in the lithography industry. He learned his trade while employed by Currier and Ives, and eventually even set up his own lithography shop. He opened his first photography studio in 1867, near 630 Broadway in New York. Otto Sarony, (1850–1903) son and heir of Napoleon Sarony, worked with his father. Otto began directing sessions that appeared under the Sarony signature in the late 1880s. He presided over virtually every session undertaken by the studio from 1893 until his father's death in 1896. From 1896 until October 7, 1898, he was sole proprietor of the business. In 1898 he sold the studio, including the trademark name "Sarony" to Jonathan Burrow. Otto Sarony managed the studio until his death in 1903. To Burrow's chagrin, in 1902 Otto Sarony had sold the right to his own name to photographic entrepreneur Theodore C. Marceau, who set up a rival studio. Sarony remained a viable brand in portrait photography until the mid-20th century.
    This subseries consists of photographs of theatrical portraits taken by Sarony and Co. between 1879-1917. Subjects include Sam Bernard, Kyle Bellew, Virginia Clark, Helen Hayes, and Maude White.
    - Theatrical Portraits A-C, 1879-1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Theatrical Portraits D-F, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Theatrical Portraits G-L, 1879-1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Theatrical Portraits M-Z, 1890-1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries: MARTHA SWOPE, 1961-1987
    This subseries consists of photos taken by Martha Swope (1928-2017), founder of Swope Associates. Swope was a former dancer who began her photographic career in the 1950s as a freelance photographer specializing in dance and theater. Included here are photos of the original casts of Broadway shows, both in theatrical productions and in the rehearsal process, shot by Swope for publicity and documentary purposes.
    Productions include "84 Charing Cross Road," "A Chorus Line," "Da," "Harold and Maude," "I Never Sang for My Father," and "Pippin," among many others.
    - Theatrical Productions A, 1966-1983, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Theatrical Productions B, 1961-1987, undated (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    - Theatrical Productions C, 1968-1986 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
    - Theatrical Productions D, 1970-1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    - Theatrical Productions E-F, 1969-1986 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Theatrical Productions G-H, 1963-1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Theatrical Productions I-K, 1969-1980 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Theatrical Productions L, 1970-1983 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Productions M-N, 1969-1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Theatrical Productions O, 1970-1983 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Theatrical Productions P, 1963-1983 (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
    - Theatrical Productions R, 1963-1984 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Theatrical Productions S, 1968-1986 (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
    - Theatrical Productions T, 1961-1985 (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
    - Theatrical Productions U-Z, 1963-1985 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Theatrical Productions Unidentified, 1971-1972, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Theatrical Portraits, 1976-1983 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: VANDAMM STUDIOS, 1926-1958
    This subseries contains the work of Vandamm Studio, founded by Florence Vandamm (1883-1966). Vandamm Studio, in operation in New York from 1924 to 1964, was run by Florence Vandamm and her husband George R. Thomas, and the photographs capture the New York theater world. This subseries includes images of theatrical productions and portraits of stage actors.
    This subseries contains photos of plays such as "Angels in the Wings," "Bloomer Girl," "Doctor's Dilemma," "The Good Fairy," "Madame Bovary," "Star Wagon," and "Streets of New York," among many others. Portrait subjects include Mary Boland, Jimmy Durante, Helen Hayes, Harriet Jackson, Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne.
    - Theatrical Productions A, 1930-1951, undated (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Theatrical Productions B, 1929-1954, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Productions C, 1928-1950, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Theatrical Productions D, 1933-1955 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Theatrical Productions E-F, 1936-1953, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Theatrical Productions G, 1931-1936 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Theatrical Productions H, 1927-1947 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Theatrical Productions I, 1937, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Theatrical Productions J, 1934-1945 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Theatrical Productions K, 1942-1943 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Productions L, 1942-1953, undated (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
    - Theatrical Productions M, 1933-1951 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
    - Theatrical Productions N, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Theatrical Productions O, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Theatrical Productions P, 1926-1958 (Box 15, Folder 10-11)
    - Theatrical Productions R, 1935-1948 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Theatrical Productions S, 1931-1948 (Box 16, Folder 1-3)
    - Theatrical Productions T, 1931-1950 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
    - Theatrical Productions V, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Theatrical Productions W, 1941-1950, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Theatrical Productions Y, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Portraits A-J, 1936-1948, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Portraits K-Z, 1936-1951, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Subseries: WHITE STUDIO, 1912-1933
    Founded by New Yorker Luther S. White (1857-1936), White Studio had a leading role in documenting Broadway stage productions from 1905 to 1939. This photographic agency employed a series of photographers who recorded hundreds of performers and thousands of productions of the American stage. The studio was divided into two operations: the portrait studio located on Broadway, and a mobile team of production photographers who hauled their equipment to the dress rehearsals for stage pictures. Two renowned photographers worked uncredited in the portrait studio: Edward Thayer Monroe during the 1910s and Ralph Shaklee in the 1930s.
    This subseries contains photographs of Broadway theatrical productions and portraits of actors taken by White Studio between 1913-1933. Subjects include productions of "Heavy Traffic," "Breakfast in Bed, and "The Last Laugh."
    - Theatrical Portraits A-Z, 1920-1933 (Box 17)
    - Theatrical Productions, 1912-1930 (Box 18-19)
  - Subseries: MISCELLANEOUS and unidentified Broadway theatrical photographers, 1910-1980, bulk 1910-1940
    This subseries consists of miscellaneous photographs that were grouped together by collectors/donors. It contains images of Broadway actors and stage productions by photographers and studios not found in other subseries.
    Photographers and studios include Campbell Studio, Irving Chidnoff, De Barron, John Seymour Erwin, Goldberg Studio, Ira Hill, Lucas and Monroe, Muray Studio, and Rappaport Studio.
    Arrangement
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by photographer.
    - Photographers A-J, 1910-1980 (Box 20, Folder 1-5)
    - Photographers K-Z, 1914-1979 (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
    - Unidentified photographers, 1910-1980 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - Theatrical Portraits, Oversize, 1910-1980 (Box 43)
- Series II: Hollywood Studio Photography, 1915-1990
  The Hollywood Studio Photographs series consists of images created by the photography units of the American film industry's major motion picture studios including Warner Bros, Universal, Paramount, RKO, Fox Corporation, and Columbia Pictures. The photos date from 1915-1990, and while most are studio portraits, there are also staged shots depicting subjects at home, with their families and friends, engaging in physical and outdoor activities, and modeling clothes.
  Photographs are variously labelled or stamped with sitter, production, original collection, date, studio, credit lines, and photographer; in some cases, original annotations and publicity captions are present.
  The photographers featured in this series include, among others, John Miehle, Gene Robert Richee, Roman Freulich, Clarence Sinclair Bull, Ruth Harriet Louise, Elmer Fryer, and Robert W. Coburn.
  - Subseries: KENNETH ALEXANDER, 1933-1938
    This subseries contains portraits of film actors taken by Kenneth Alexander (1887-1975), a photographer for United Artists and 21st Century Fox motion picture studios. The photographs date from 1933-1938,and include such stars as Clark Gable, Billie Burke, and Merle Oberon.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1933-1938 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Subseries: ERNEST BACHRACH, 1929-1952
    This subseries consists of photographs taken by Ernest Bachrach (1899-1973), an influential Hollywood portrait photographer. He headed the photographic department at RKO Studios from its inception in 1929 until his retirement in 1958. This subseries includes many of the stars employed by RKO during these decades, among them Jackie Cooper, Joan Fontaine, Claudette Colbert, and Mae Murray.
    .
    - Portraits A-L, 1929-1952 (Box 25, Folder 1-7)
    - Portraits M-Z, 1930-1950 (Box 26, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries: CLARENCE S. BULL, 1929-1946
    This subseries consists of photographs taken by Clarence Sinclair Bull (1896-1979), a portrait photographer who headed the stills department of MGM studios for 40 years, during the "Golden Age of Hollywood." Included in this subseries are images of actors Myrna Loy, James Stewart, Katharine Hepburn, Lena Horne, Spencer Tracy, Ingrid Bergman, and many others.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1929-1946 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Portraits Oversize, 1933-1942 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Subseries: ROBERT W. COBURN, 1931-1959
    This subseries consists of photographs taken by Robert W. Coburn (1900-1990). Coburn was a prominent Hollywood photographer in the 1930s-1960s, and worked at Columbia Pictures for 20 years.
    Included here are images of film stars such as Joan Crawford, Carole Lombard, Hedy Lamarr, Henry Fonda, Joel McCrea, Lucille Ball, Marlon Brando, Montgomery Clift, Orson Welles, Ginger Rogers, Fred Astaire, Cary Grant, Katherine Hepburn, and Kim Novak, amng many others.
    - Portraits A-C, 1931-1956 (Box 27, Folder 1-4)
    - Portraits-D-H, 1935-1948 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Portraits-J-L, 1933-1944 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Portraits-M-N, 1933-1959 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Portraits-O-S, 1933-1956 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Portraits-T-Z, 1934-1951 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Subseries: OTTO DYAR, 1928-1936
    This subseries consists of theatrical portraits shot by Otto Dyar (1892-1988), who began his career at Paramount movie studio. He photographed publicity stills and portraits of Hollywood stars. Subjects included in this subseries are William Boyd, Jackie Coogan, Paul Lukas, Richard "Skeets" Gallagher, Dorothy Hall and Claire Trevor.
    - Portraits A-F, 1930-1934 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Portraits G-J, 1930-1936 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Portraits K-M, 1928-1934 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Portraits N-Z, 1930-1935 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Subseries: DON ENGLISH, 1930-1946
    This subseries contains photographs taken by Don English (1901-1964) who worked in the camera department of Paramount studios in the 1930s and 1940s. It includes a set of still photographs from the 1941 movie "Caught in the Draft" starring Bob Hope and Dorothy Lamour.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1930-1946 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Set photographs "Caught in the Draft", 1941 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Subseries: ROMAN FREULICH, 1922-1947
    This subseries consists of photographs taken by Polish-American photographer Roman Freulich (1898-1974) between 1922-1947. Freulich trained with New York photographer Samuel Lumiere before moving to Hollywood in 1922 to work as a still photographer at Universal Studio.He later worked for Republic Studios and United Artists.
    Among the subjects include here are Hedda Hopper, Martha Raye, Jean Hersholt, and George Larkin.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1922-1947 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries: ELMER FRYER, 1930-1947
    This subseries contains photographs taken by Elmer Fryer (1898-1944). He worked as head photographer at Warner Brothers Studio from 1929 to 1941, capturing major film stars of the 1930s. Included here are portraits of Bette Davis, Joe E. Brown, Josephine Hutchinson, and Lyle Talbot, among others.
    - Portraits A-H, 1933-1941 (Box 29, Folder 1-5)
    - Portraits I-Z, 1930-1942 (Box 29, Folder 6-12)
    - Portraits Oversize, 1937-1947 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Subseries: RAY JONES, 1932-1947
    This subseries consists of photographs by Ray Jones (1892-1967) chief portrait photographer at Universal Studios from 1935 to 1958. Subjects of these photos, taken between 1932 and 1947, include Charles Boyer, Jackie Coogan, and Eliza Logan, among others.
    - Portraits A-F, 1932-1945 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Portraits G-J, 1934-1947 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Portraits K-O, 1935-1946 (Box 30, Folder 3)